A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of James A. Gardner FA629
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of James A. Gardner
1971-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA629
0.88 Cubic Feet
The Latin America and Caribbean Papers of James A. Gardner document his activities and those of the International Division primarily for the period Gardner served as the Program Officer/Coordinator for the Caribbean from 1974 to 1977. They were transferred to the Foundation's Archives in July 1982. These papers consist of correspondence, and reports which were retained in the office of James Gardner when he served in New York as the Program Officer/ Coordinator for the Caribbean.
Biographical / Historical
James A. Gardner, Ford Foundation Representative for the Latin America and Caribbean office of the International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from 1969 until 1981. During this period, he held the following positions:
• February 1977, Representative, LA&C, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, ID • September 1974, Program Officer, LA&C, Coordinator for the Caribbean, New York, ID • September 1973, Program Officer, LA&C, on one year study leave at the Harvard Law School, ID • February 1972, Program Officer and Assistant to Head, LA&C, ID • August 1971, Assistant Program Officer and Assistant to Head, LA&C, ID • July 1969, Assistant to the Representative, LA&C, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, ID
James Gardner was born July 22, 1943. He received his B.A. degree in 1965 from Harvard University. In 1968, he earned the J.D. degree from the Yale Law School.
Prior to Gardner's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
• 1966 - 1968 Resident Counselor and Advisor, Yale University • 1968 - 1969 Assistant Director of Admissions and Tutor in Social Sciences and Law, Harvard University
After his departure from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Gardner accepted the position of President of Lewis and Clark College of Portland, Oregon.
Scope and Contents
The two boxes of correspondence and reports which constitute the LAC Papers of James A. Gardner, document his activities and a number of those of the International Division for the years 1971 to 1977.
The papers contain material on the subject of human rights, including the Foundation's policy statement regarding biomedical research and the use of human beings as subjects.
The files discuss the subject of law and its social obligations. In particular, they illuminate such topics as law and development, social change, and how it relates to the development of human talent; the future of public interest law; and Gardner's work, "The Legal Profession and the Third World," which deals with American assistance to legal education in Latin America in the 1960's.
The papers also contain related correspondence between LAC staff members and individuals who applied for the FY76 Foundation sponsored Caribbean Fellowship Fund, but whose applications were incomplete.
The Correspondence Files document the day-to-day program activity of Gardner during his New York based tenure as the Program Officer/Coordinator for the Caribbean.
Arrangement
The Latin America and Caribbean Papers of James A. Gardner, are divided into two series:
I. Subject Files
II. Correspondence Files
Arrangement within the series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Gardner's office.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned reports. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Subject Files, 1971-1976; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Subject Files (1971-1976), are the most substantive. They contain material on the following: human rights; law and development; law and social sciences; law and social change; public interest law; and FY76 Caribbean fellowship fund (incomplete) application requests. The material consists of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports.
  Arrangement
  The files are arranged in reverse calendar order. Within each folder, the files are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Human Rights, 1974 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
  - Law and Development, 1971 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21-35)
  - Law and Social Sciences, 1972 - 1973; 1975 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 36-39)
  - Law and Social Change, 1976 October (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Public Interest Law, 1974 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
  - FY76 Caribbean fellowship fund (incomplete) application requests, 1975 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
- Correspondence Files, 1974-1976; II
  Series II, Correspondence Files (1974-1976), document the office activities of Gardner during his tenure as the Program Officer/Coordinator for the Caribbean. Recipients of his outgoing correspondence and interoffice memoranda include FF colleagues, grantee and membership organizations, and individuals and organizations seeking grants.
  - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 46-55)
  - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 56-67)
  - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 68-79)
- Appendix A: James A. Gardner Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished Ford Foundation reports by James Gardner were removed from the papers. They are listed in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Caribbean Budget Proposals, FY 75-77, 1975 February (Report 9461)
  - First Organizational Meeting and Conference Caribbean Studies Association, 1975 February (Report 8844)
  - The Foundation - Grantee Relationship (Report 8922)
  - ILC Research and Advisory Committee on Law and Development, Second Meeting, 1973 February (Report 5934)
  - Law and Development: Review of an Evolving School of Inquiry, 1972 May (Report 5936)
  - Law and Social Change, Law and Human Choice: The Ford Foundation and International Programs in Law in the 1980's (Report 7399)
  - The Legal Profession and the Third World: A Critical History of the Law and Development Movement, with Particular Reference to Latin America (Report 6186)
  - Population/Family Planning Explorations in Jamaica, Gardner and Nagel, June 11-13, 1975 June (Report 6803)
  - Tenth West Indies Agricultural Economic Conference, Georgetown, Guyana: "Maximizing Regional Self-Sufficiency in the Commonwealth Caribbean, 1975 May (Report 8723)
- Appendix B: Ford Foundation Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished reports written by other FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers. They are listed alphabetically by author. For each author, the reports are arranged in alphabetical order. The number at the left is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Bell, David. Discussions with Human Rights Groups in Europe, 1976 May (Report 8839)
  - Drysdale, Robert. Social Sciences and the Ford Foundation, 1976 April (Report 8912)
  - Heaps, David. Draft Report on Human Rights, 1975 August (Report 5643)
  - Heaps, David. Human Rights and Intellectual Freedom, 1975 August (Report 2256)
  - Heaps, David. Human Rights Conference, January 19, 1976, 1976 January (Report 9460)
  - Heaps, David. Human Rights Paper, n.d. (Report 65)
  - Heaps, David. International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) Proposals for Foundation Considerations, 1976 August (Report 43)
  - Krueger, Starry. AMIK # 71-51 monitoring report, 1971 September (Report 6511)
  - Latif, Shahed. A Report on the Visit to Cuba, financed by the Ford Foundation, 1974 July (Report 5922)
  - Miller, William. The Improvement of the System Within the System: Notes on the the Ethos of American Liberal Reform, n.d. (Report 6057)
  - Myers, Robert. Notes on Building Capacity for Educational Research, 1975 October (Report 7002)
  - Myers, Robert. Trip to Jamaica, 1975 October (Report 9416)
  - Seay, George. Statistical Data on the Caribbean Territories, 1973 August (Report 9462)
  - Silvert, Kalman. In Search of Theoretical Room for Freedom: North American Social Science Thinking About Latin American Development, 1976 March (Report 8918)
  - Silvert, Kalman. The Foundation, The Social Sciences, and Latin America, 1976 April (Report 5065)